Cartes de visite Collection
Cartes de visite Collection
1859-1900
Cartes de visite.
1 linear ft. (1 box, 322 photographs)
Cartes de visite of the 19th century including albumen prints, platinotypes, tintypes and several lithographs. Included are works by American, European, and Asian photographers: Abdullah Freres, E. & H.T. Anthony, Brady National Photographic Art Gallery, J.H. Bufford, Alexander Gardner, London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company, William E. Marshall, Mora, A. Sachtler, and Napoleon Sarony. Subjects include celebrities, family portraits, indigenous peoples, soldiers, and travel photos from America, Europe, China, Japan, and the Malay Pennisula.
149516
Biographical History
The carte de visite, sometimes hyphenated as carte-de-visite, was a type of small photograph which originated in France in the late 1850s and became immensely popular in both Europe and the United States. It consisted of a thin paper photograph (usually an albumen print) mounted on a thicker paper card, about the size of a modern-day playing card. Their popularity led to the production of cards with photographs of notable people, which were collected and traded.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cartes de visite Collection Collection includes albumen prints, platinotypes, tintypes and several lithographs. Included are works by American, European, and Asian photographers: Abdullah Freres, E. & H.T. Anthony, Brady National Photographic Art Gallery, J.H. Bufford, Alexander Gardner, London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company, William E. Marshall, Mora, A. Sachtler, and Napoleon Sarony. Subjects include celebrities, family portraits, indigenous peoples, soldiers, and travel photos from America, Europe, China, Japan, and the Malay Pennisula.
"Most of the pre-1867 images [in the Chinese and Japanese character titles] seem to have been taken by European photographers. About 1880-1885, cheap copy issues of both Chinese and Japanese series appeared in the market. These often bear titles in characters only, suggesting that they were intended for local distribution and not for sale in Europe or America." (Durrah, p. 64)
Arrangement of the Collection
Cards are divided into American and foreign; within that, the majority are arranged alphabetically by photographer. All items are in a single box.
Subject and Genre Headings
Photography; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896.; Bufford, J. H.; Gardner, Alexander, 1821-1882.; Mora.; Sachtler, A.; Sarony, Napoleon.; Walker, Mary Edwards, 1832-1919.; E. & H.T. Anthony (Firm); Brady's National Photographic Portrait Galleries.; Abdullah frères.; London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company.; Altered prints.; Albumen paper.; Carte de visite photographs.; Lithography -- 19th century.; Photography -- 19th century.; Photograph collections.; Portrait photography -- 19th century.; Tintype.; Travel photography.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Photography.; Albumen prints.; Cartes-de-visite.; Lithographs.; Photographs.; Platinum prints.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- American
  - A, 1 packet
    - R. W. Addis, Unidentified soldier
    - Anson, General Mitchele
    - Anthony & Co., Handel, Rossini, Ruber, Verdi
    - E. & H. T. Anthony, H[enry] Clay, A[ndrew] G[regg] Curtin (governor of Pennsylvania, 1861-1867); Admiral DuPont; Percival Drayton, U. S. N. (1860); Duryear? [revenue stamp] (Aug. 18, 1864); Charles Elliot; Gen. Grant; Kilpatrick [revenue stamp] (Aug. 18, 1864)
    - L. A. Atwood, unidentified man (portrait); unidentified woman
  - B, 1 packet
    - W. J. Baker, Rosa D'Erina, Erin's prima donna
    - Chas. K. Bill, 1860; Com. J. E. Barry, U.S.N.
    - T. H. Blair, unidentified young man
    - [A] Bogardus, Col. R. Ward; unidentified man [revenue stamp]
    - Bolton, unidentified woman
    - [M] Brady, William ? Phila. (1876); G. H. Thomas; unidentified man, head & shoulders [vignetted]; unidentified man, standing
    - J. Sidney Brown, Dan G. Taylor
    - J. W. Bryant, unidentified girl
    - Burlington Photo. Co., unidentified young woman
    - Burnham, unidentified man; class supper; bouquet presented by the Misses French and Wright, ladies of class [18]84 (March 22, 1881); football piece (1884 [?])
    - Burns, unidentified man
    - D. C. Burnite, unidentified woman, seated [revenue stamp]
  - C, 1 packet
    - R. F. Channell, unidentified man, seated; unidentified man, standing
    - T. W. Clark, unidentified man [vignette]
    - Geo. N. Cobb, unidentified couple; three children
    - Cobb & Hempstead, unidentified man [vignetted]
  - D, 1 packet
    - Darnell, unidentified man
    - Decamp & Crane, unidentified woman, standing [revenue stamp]; unidentified woman [vignetted, revenue stamp]
    - O. R. DeMorat, Corpl. H. C? Shearer, D 'Co' "187" [revenue stamp]
    - S. Dome & Co., unidentified child [hand tinted, revenue stamp]
  - E, 1 packet
    - Charles W. Eberman, unidentified woman [revenue stamp]
    - Ennis, John L. Sullivan
    - Dr. J. W. Ewing, unidentified man [partially hand tinted]
  - F, 1 packet
    - F. Forshew, unidentified woman, standing; unidentified man; composer Georgia R. Rockwell
    - Joseph B. Forster, American physician Mary Edwards Walker, standing, wearing bloomer costume
    - A. J. Fox, unidentified boy [revenue stamp]
    - C. D. Fredricks & Co., unidentified man [vignetted]
    - Fredericks & Hopkins, Lena Dorr
  - G, 1 packet
    - Gardner, unidentified man
    - Alex. Gardner, Ewyn B. Fariatus? 1861
    - Chas. L. Gillingham, unidentified woman; "your love, Lotta"
    - Gills City Gallery, unidentified couple [revenue stamp]
    - Gilmore's Gallery of Art, two unidentified men seated
    - John Goldin & Co., Gen. Wm. A. Averill [revenue stamp]
    - Groom's Photographic Gallery, Two unidentified men seated [revenue stamp]
    - L. D. Griffin, unidentified young woman standing
    - W. G. Grottecloss, unidentified woman, standing, [revenue stamp] (Jul. 9, 1966); unidentified man, seated [revenue stamp] (Jul. 14, 1886)
    - Gurney & Son, Rose Hersee, "What's in a Name?"; Aimee
    - F. Gutekunst, "Col John Falconer wounded before Richmond and died in a few days."; unidentified soldier, standing; "For Professor Stoddard with the compliments of O. S. Glipov, Comd. U. S. Navy."; Dr. Blaker 22d Mich. late of 23d Mich.
  - H, 1 packet
    - Haines, G.? P.? Rockwell [vignette]
    - Happy Hours Company, all are red-orange cards, printed in gold: E. L. Davenport; John Brougham; George Peabody; Maggie Mitchell; Clara Louise Kellogg; Brignoli
    - J. B. Hazleton, unidentified woman seated [revenue stamp]
    - Hazleton & Deans, unidentified couple, [revenue stamp] (Sept. 28, 1864)
    - C. O. Hodgman, "Sincerely yours, A. M. Wavinksle [?] Lt. U.S. Navy, November 1877"
    - Hoelke & Benecke, Gov. Gamble [vignetted]
    - J. B. Hopkins, unidentified woman standing "Carried through five months imprisonment at Salisbery, Dauirlle & Richmond."
    - J. Horning's Photographic Rooms, "Yours, Frank Best" [revenue stamp]
    - Hotchkiss, unidentified man
    - Howe, unidentified man [vignetted]
    - F. L. Huff, unidentified child
  - I - L, 1 packet
    - Israel & Co., unidentified man standing [revenue stamp]
    - Johnson's National Gallery, unidentified man, standing
    - J. O. Kane, published by, E. M. Stanton, Sec. of War
    - J. Kirk, unidentified man, seated [revenue stamp]
    - C. B. Knowles, unidentified woman; unidentified man; unidentified child (3)
    - Isaac S. Lachman, unidentified child [revenue stamp]
    - Larkin Gallery, unidentified child
    - J. C. Lesher, unidentified woman
    - W. O. Luke, unidentified woman; unidentified man
  - M, 1 packet
    - Wm. E. Marshall, unidentified man [vignette]
    - P. B. Marvin (Addis Gallery), unidentified man [vignette]
    - Miller & Rowell, John Albion Andrew, 21st Governor of Massachusetts, 1861
    - W. B. Miles, unidentified man; unidentified woman
    - Mora, Annie Louise Carey; Offenbach; Anna W. Tiffany
    - G. D. Morse, unidentified child [hand tinted]
    - Morse's Gallery of the Cumberland, George Armitage? [vignette, revenue stamp]; R. S. Dodd [revenue stamp]; Geo. H. Winslow [revenue stamp]; unidentified man, standing
    - Moray & Sturdevant, unidentified man
    - L. C. Mundy, "What are you going to do about it?" circa 1878
    - Mundy & Rowell, unidentified child
    - C. H. McAllister, unidentified man
    - J. McMillen, unidentified man, standing
  - N - O, 1 packet
    - The New York Photographic Co., Sheridan [vignetted]
    - Austen & Oliver, "Oswego Nov. 28, 1875 From her Uncle BBB"
    - F. W. Oliver (Late Austen & Oliver), Mifs. T. E.
    - Owen's Gallery, unidentified man
    - I. G. Owen, unidentified man (3); unidentified woman (8); "Compliments of M. H. Leidmose?"
  - P - R, 1 packet
    - Peck Bros., [Yale College Durrah p. 99] 1860
    - Percival's Gallery, unidentified women [vignetted]
    - Pierce & Richardson, unidentified woman [revenue stamp] June, 1866?
    - M. J. Powers, [map] Position of the 1st Brig. 1st Div. 9th Corp. Before Petersburg, Va.
    - E. M. Recher, unidentified woman seated [revenue stamp]
    - J. F. Ryder, Admiral [?]
  - S, 1 packet
    - Sarony, William [Cullen] Bryant; Miss Mollenhauser; Miss Stockman; Edward Sothern as Lord Dundreary in "The American Cousin"; unidentified woman [vignetted]
    - Saylor's New Photographic Gallery, unidentified child, standing; unidentified child, standing
    - T. M. Schleier, unidentified man [vignetted]
    - A. J. Schillare, unidentified woman [vignetted]
    - J. A. Scholten, Fremont & Seagle? copy from a painting by C. Wimar?
    - Louis Seebohm, Charles Kette U.S.?, 1861
    - W. T. Seely, Capt. A. L. Wilson
    - Sharpsteen, Dan Hamilton
    - Shaw's Mammoth Photographic Rooms, unidentified scene
    - J. Rennie Smith, unidentified woman; unidentified man
    - Soule, unidentified woman standing ([vignetted, revenue stamp]
    - Stoutenburgh & Rose, unidentified woman standing [revenue stamp]; unidentified man, seated
  - U - Z, 1 packet
    - Henry Ulke, Francis H. Hines [revenue stamp] August 23, 1868
    - J. H. Van Travoren, Ike Bself? [revenue stamp] July 4, 1865; unidentified young man standing [revenue stamp]
    - Vaughn, unidentified woman "Nelson N. Bancroft, Co. G 62nd regt."; N.Y. Vol. 1 Brig. 2 Div. 6th Corps. Washington, D. C." [vignetted]
    - Warren, Titians [woman in velvet dress standing]
    - Wenderoth, Taylor & Brown, "Rolana, my aunt at the age of 86." [revenue stamp]
    - Wenderoth & Taylor, W. P. Penn 1863; "To Miss Amelia, Brittin House with the respectful souvenir & Christian regard of her grateful brother in ? C. Chiniquy? Fte. Anne? Kan Kaker Co. Illinois 26 July 1864."
    - Williams, unidentified man [vignetted]
    - L. B. Williams, Georgia R. Rockwell
    - Geo. H. Wood, unidentified man, seated
    - Wormell, unidentified woman, standing
    - Young & Platt, J. P. McEldeny?
    - F. M. Zuller, "To Wm. P. Moran Esq. with respects of Cecil C. Neil December 16, 1872."
- Foreign countries (by photographer)
  - Photographer unknown, 2 packets
    - Miscellaneous countries: China, Sumatra, Malay, Java, etc.
  - A. Sachtler, Singapore, 1 packet
    - Birmese [Burmese] Idol, Rangoon
    - Rajah of Chenribon, Java
    - Unidentified man, writing illegible
    - Singapore view
    - Unidentified temple
    - Temple at Rangoon, Birmah [Burma]
    - Emp'or of Pooley [?], Java
    - Malay woman, standing
    - Dalhonsin? Pien
    - "A. Louen? at?" woman, standing
    - Singapore view
    - Cocoa Nut Grove
    - Unidentified view
    - Javanese unidentified woman, seated
    - Armenian unidentified man, standing
    - Cocoanut grove, Singapore
    - Palm
    - Chinese Temples, Singapore
    - Singapore View
    - Prince Absoran Samaranj, Java
    - Singapore View
    - Madras Officer
    - Unidentified View
    - Courthouse & Post Office, Singapore
    - Unidentified man, seated
    - Kling merchant
  - T. Haywood and D. Watson, St. Helena, Simonstown[?], 1 packet
    - Jamestown Harbor
    - Jamestown Harbor
    - Jamestown and Harbor returning from the Tomb of Napoleon
    - Tomb of Napoleon
    - Distant view of Napoleon's Tomb from the road
    - Spring of water at the Tomb of Napoleon
    - Unidentified view
    - Unidentified view
  - Series with printed captions in English, 1 packet
    - "A Common 'Kangho' or chair."
    - "As pensive I thought," etc.
    - "Bettoes resting in teahouse"
    - "Sampans" [with paragraphs of explanation]
  - Chinese or Japanese character titles, 1 packet
    - Seated woman, circa 1880-1885
    - Four Women, circa 1880-1885
    - Group, men, women, children, circa 1880-1885
- Foreign (by country or city)
  - B, 1 packet
    - Berlin
      - R. Marowsky, Mr. & Mrs. Julius J. Krochl
      - Gustav Schauer, Alex. V. Humboldt's Portrait, Begas.
  - C-W, 1 packet
    - Canton, China
      - Photographer unknown, Feb. 17, 1875; Whoy Esmorehouse
    - Copenhagen
      - L. Hartmann, woman standing
    - Constantinople
      - Abdullah Freres, "Brother of the Sultan that will take the throne when Sultan dies"
    - Egypt
      - Schier & Schoefft, Beverly Kennow, Egyptian Army
    - England
      - Photographer unknown, H.R.H. Alfred Ernest Albert
      - Henry P. Robinson, soldier standing
      - Messr's W. Walker & Sons, unidentified man
      - The London Stereoscopic & Photographic Company, Mrs. Scott Siddons
    - Germany?
      - BK or KB, Furst Bismarck; Graf Von Moltke; Kronprinz v. Preussen; Konig Wilhelm T.v. Preussen
    - Lima
      - V. L. Richardson, circa 1875?
    - Lisbon
      - F. Rocchini, Belim Castle
    - Paris
      - E. Neurdein, Duc d'Orleans; Francois Joseph I; Marie Amelie; Bulla Freres
      - Nauma Fils, unidentified painting
      - Susse Fres Estienne & Cie, Lt. Gregory
    - Plau[en]
      - Aug. Ehrich, unidentified woman seated
    - Wien
      - Rabending und Monckhoven, Empress Elizabeth of Austria
- Miscellaneous
  - Photographer unknown, subject identified, 1 packet
    - S. Armsby...Rice Co. Minn.
    - Count Bismarck
    - W. R. Bridgmann U.S.N.
    - Dr. Cummings, Lt. B. F. Brisco Co. "H", Lt. U. S. Davis Co. "H" and acting 2r Mr 23d Mich. Vol. Infty.
    - Camille Dubois
    - Gen. Dwight, Bank's Staff
    - "Jerome Falconer, wounded at the battle of 'Stoneriver' and after six months of great suffering from his wounds yielded up his life a sacrifice on his country's alter"
    - Rear Adm'l D. G. Farragut
    - G. W. Harding, Owatonna? Co. Minnesota
    - Emma W. Henry
    - Empress Josephine
    - Abraham Lincoln and his family from a painting
    - Pauling Lucca
    - Thomas Lullus? News Agent 5th Corps, Army Potomac, 1861
    - M. E. Church, N. Y. (interior)
    - M. E. Church, N. Y. (interior organ)
    - Geo. Norris? or Morris? (black man, seated)
    - Louis Napoleon
    - Carlotta Patti sister of Adelina
    - Jas. M. Prichett?
    - Lulu Pryor
    - J. F. Richardson
    - Buckalew Pa. [?possibly Charles Buckalew, lawyer from Blooomberg, Pennsylvania]
    - Secor
    - O. L. Spaulding
    - H. S. Stellwageu?
    - Major Gen. Geo H. Thomas
    - Verdi
    - Ida Yerance
    - Civil War General
    - "The man hung at close of the war for trying to set fire to N. Y."
    - Motherless
    - The Union Generals
    - War widow
  - Photographer unknown, subject unidentified, 1 packet
    - Miscellaneous
- Lithographs
  - Miscellaneous, 1 packet
    - America
      - J. H. Bufford, Pub., Joseph Hooker, Maj. Gen. Comd. Div.; Major Genl. Franz Siegel
      - J. A. O'Neile, unidentified man
    - England
      - The London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company, unidentified man [color]
    - Unknown country of origin
      - Constant Cook & Wm. H. Russell, Maj. Gen. Hancock Liberty
- Tintypes
  - Miscellaneous, 1 packet